Katherine Scroggins

Elementary Education Teacher with ESL Endorsement and Early Years Education

Phoenix, AZ 85041 | katjr180@hotmail.com

Professional Summary

To empower students on their learning journey, by being active participants in provocations, which balance foundation learning and hands-on exploration. I will achieve this goal by initiating student-led inquiries, encouraging student agency, and by creating a stimulating and safe learning environment.

Core Competencies

- Student-led inquiries
- Reading program development
- Social Skills program development
- PYP unit planning and assessment adaptation
- Seesaw implementation and management
- Managebac reporting and reflection
- Reader's Workshop and Writer's Workshop
- Jolly Phonics instruction
- Reggio Emilia philosophy application
- Parent communication and presentations

Key Achievements & Strengths

Reading Program Development: Helped develop a reading program that increased the Primary School's overall reading average.

Social Skills Program: Developed a program focusing on communication, recognizing feelings, and setting boundaries.

Leadership: Lead for team in Seesaw implementation, an online portfolio and documentation application.

Curriculum Development: Co-wrote Kindergarten curriculum ensuring balance and student-led learning.

Reggio Emilia Implementation: Applied Reggio philosophies to social and emotional programs and learning experiences.

Parent Engagement: Presented curriculum and learning approaches to parents to encourage participation.

Certifications

- Jolly Phonics Online Course
- NFHS Football/Soccer Coach Certification
- Training on Middle Management Leadership
- Completed PYP courses in Concepts based, Reading and Writing

Professional Experience

EY5/Kindergarten Teacher

August 2018-Present

St. John's International School

- Helped develop a reading program that increased the Primary School's overall reading average.
- Helped develop Social Skills program focusing on communication, recognizing feelings, and setting boundaries.
- Adapted PYP unit planners and assessments with colleagues.
- Lead for team in Seesaw implementation, an online portfolio and documentation application.
- Used Managebac to record and reflect on PYP Units and report cards.
- Experience and training using Reader's Workshop, Writer's Workshop, and Jolly Phonics.
- Presented to parents about Language Arts and Maths curriculum.

Early Learning School Coordinator

August 2019-2021

St. John's International School

- Revamped and updated Literacy Program by introducing Jolly Phonics, starting weekly journaling, and creating a book room for independent student checkouts.
- Implemented Reggio philosophies to develop Social and Emotional program encouraging choices, naming emotions, and peer interaction strategies.
- Encouraged use of outdoor spaces for Messy Maths and other learning experiences.

Kindergarten Teacher

August 2017-July 2018

Leipzig International Kindergarten

- Co-wrote the Kindergarten curriculum ensuring it was balanced and student-led.
- Developed Reggio-based documentation and dialogue encouraging parent-school communication and participation.

Presented at "Students' Voices in the Early Years" 2018 AGIS Conferences.

Grade 1 Teacher

August 2016-June 2017
International School of Ulm-Neu-Ulm

- Assisted school in PYP accreditation and wrote self-reflection study reports on curriculum and philosophy.
- Developed student-led unit-based curriculum.
- Developed documentation and dialogue encouraging parent-school communication and participation.

Early Years Teacher (3-6 year olds)

August 2011-June 2016

The KAUST Schools, Thuwal-Jeddah, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia

- Gained four years of PYP experience with ECC and Kindergarten children.
- Received training on and implemented Reggio based learning experiences for students and parents.
- Presented lectures for colleagues based on Reggio and Play-based classroom experiences.

Consulting History

Mentor and Trainer Ongoing, Various

- Mentored student teachers and assistants.
- Completed Jolly Phonics Online Course.
- Attended Reggio Emilia Work Study Group to implement Reggio inspired experiences.
- Co-created a Preschool Center and Kindergarten program.

Education

Bachelor of Science in Elementary Education (Kindergarten-Grade 8), Northern Arizona University — 2002 (with ESL Endorsement K-12 and Early Years Education)